so let's look at the system that is not
even unusual that combines all of these
three forms of parallelism so we can
have a dual socket motherboard that has
two chips with four cores on each chip
and each core can simultaneously run two
threads using simultaneous
multi-threading so as far as the
programmer is concerned and as far as
the operating system is concerned what
we really have is two times four times
two which means that 16 threads or for
that matter 16 different single threaded
programs can run simultaneously and a
relatively simple operating system would
just treat these as 16 largely
equivalent course this can be a big
problem because let's say that we
actually have three threads and the
operating system not knowing any better
just Maps them to the first three
threads that it has but it turns out
that these two are really threads on the
same core that compete with each other
for issue slots and other things in an
out-of-order processor and then really
the first half of these threads eight of
them are really on the same shape so
we're using only half of the overall
cash capacity that the system has pretty
much we have a very large cash in the
other chip that we are not using so a
much smarter policy for using three
threads would be to put them on
different ships if we can and definitely
on different cores if we can so that
they don't compete so the idea would be
that you would first run threads such
that they're distributed among the chip
so that you maximize the cache capacity
that you're benefiting from then we also
want to make sure that we first map a
thread to each core and only then do we
want to actually map threads to the
second thread in each core so that if
there are few threads they don't need to
share the resources of the same core
each gets its own core and that requires
the operating system to actually know
what's going on so most of the
well-known operating systems like
Windows and Linux and so on will
actually be able to figure the
salt but that means that as we have this
fancy hardware that has parallelism at
different levels of granularity we also
have to make our operating systems aware
of that so it's not just expose more
thread contexts that the operating
system can use it actually matters how
you use this thread context